"Does Astragalus Have Benefits
for Life Extension and Fighting Cancer?"
In 2008, it was reported
that a screening
of traditional
Chinese medicine plants
identified a compound
called cycloastragenol
in the roots
of the astragalus plant
that appeared
to moderately enhance
telomerase activation.
That's an enzyme
I've covered before
that our body uses
to try to reverse one aspect
of cellular aging
by elongating your telomeres,
the protective caps
on your chromosomes.
Three years later,
after it was shown
to elongate short telomeres
and improve healthspan
(though not lifespan) in mice,
a one-year human trial
was published.
Although in most of the subjects
telomeres continued
to shorten on average,
there did seem to be
a significant reduction
in the proportion of cells
with critically short telomeres.
And the side effects
looked good,
including a drop
in LDL cholesterol
and blood pressure.
But there was no control group
and cycloastragenol
(branded as "TA-65")
was but one
of over fifty vitamins,
minerals, herbs,
and other compounds they gave
to the research subjects
that year.
When TA-65 was finally
properly put to the test
in randomized controlled trials,
there was no cholesterol
or blood pressure benefit
whatsoever,
but in cytomegalovirus-positive
patients,
a significant
telomere-lengthening effect
was demonstrated at one dose
but not another.
(Those with
chronic viral infections,
such as CMV or HIV,
tend to have white blood cells
with especially truncated
telomeres.)
The only such study
showing clinical benefit
was a year-long pilot study
of TA-65
for early age-related
macular degeneration,
though it was funded
by the company
that sells it
for $600 a bottle.
They grossed
more than $50 million
before the Federal
Trade Commission charged them
with false and deceptive
claims and practices.
That $600
buys you less than a gram
of astragalus root extract.
You can buy
astragalus root extract in bulk
50,000 times cheaper
for less than $20 a pound,
should there ever be
independently verified benefits.
Astragalus root,
well-known as huáng qí in China,
is one of the most popular herbs
in traditional Chinese medicine,
included in hundreds
of herbal formulas
and evidently widely marketed
for millennia
as a "life prolonging" tonic.
No data on that,
but about 30 grams a day
appeared to help
with a type
of autoimmune kidney disease
called idiopathic
membranous nephropathy
in 50 randomized
controlled trials,
but not
placebo-controlled trials;
so, any placebo effects
can't be discounted.
Pregnant or nursing women
are cautioned against
using astragalus,
and a theoretical concern
was raised
that it may activate
a certain oncogene,
a potentially
cancer-causing gene.
However,
dozens of randomized trials
of astragalus-based
herbal preparations
as an add-on therapy
to chemotherapy
for the most common type
of lung cancer
(non-small-cell) found,
if anything,
astragalus to be protective.
Lung cancer is the leading cause
of cancer death in the U.S.
Adding astragalus
to standard platinum-based chemo
reduced the risk of death
as much as 38 percent
at the one-year-mark,
and 25 percent at two years.
However, in almost all trials,
the astragalus was just one
of many herbs used in a formula,
making the effects of astragalus
impossible to tease out,
and unfortunately,
publication bias
is widespread
in the traditional
Chinese medicine literature,
where inconvenient results
may be quietly shelved,
though this in no way
unique to that field.
Similar remarkable results,
with similar critical caveats,
were published for
astragalus-containing formulas
for colorectal cancer,
including
improved quality of life.
Same thing with cervical cancer,
with remarkably reduced
chemotherapy toxicity:
less nausea and vomiting,
less hair loss,
less nerve damage,
and less liver
and kidney toxicity.
Also, less lung damage
from radiation treatments,
and for stomach cancer,
improved quality of life
and quantity of life.